so we need a directory that will fit on
chip otherwise to maintain coherence
between our caches that are very very
fast we would need to look up a
directory in very very slow memory which
kind of defeats the purpose of having
these caches some of the questions about
this directory are easy to answer like
for example where is the home node where
we go to find the directory information
about the block and the answer to that
is the same tile that has the last level
cache slice where that block would be
because if the directory entry for that
block indicates that none of the private
caches have it then we want to look up
the last level cache to find that block
so we might as well do that in the same
node that has a directory otherwise
there will be a lot of traffic between
where the directory for a block is and
where the last level cache for the block
is so naturally they should be on the
same node but that doesn't really answer
the question of having a directory entry
for every memory block we have seen that
we only keep the data in the last level
cache slides for those blocks that we
actually have in our level 3 cache but a
directory without any changes would need
to be for every possible memory block
that might ever come into that slice
which is a big problem because there are
a lot of memory blocks so instead of
keeping a director entry for every
memory block we need to realize that the
entries that are not in our last level
cache or in any caches on chip really
are not shared by anybody so we don't
really have to maintain that information
so we will maintain what is called a
partial directory we don't maintain a
directory entry for every memory block
instead our directory will have a
limited number of entries and then we
allocate and enter in this limited
directory only for such blocks that have
at least one presence bit at one they
basically only for blocks that might be
in at least one of the private caches so
for a block for which we know that it is
not in any L1 or L2 cache it's present
only in the LLC or only in memory for
that matter we don't need a directory
entry because implicitly we know that
such a directory entry would just be all
zeros but let's say that we have decided
on some limited number of entries we
start allocating those entries when we
put blocks in L2 and L1 caches and
eventually we will run out of directory
entries what do we do now